this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
SC radio is brought to you by the IEEE
computer Society IEEE software Magazine
online at computer.org software
[Music]
are you a software engineer developer
consultant architect manager no matter
what your role is we want to hear from
you please take a minute to complete our
listener survey to help us make SE radio
even more relevant to you
just go to se radio.net
survey2023 to share with us that's
se-radio.net survey2023
thanks for your support of the show
welcome to software engineering radio
I'm your host Gregory kaphammer today's
guest is Zach Lloyd the founder and CEO
of warp a startup dedicated to helping
software Engineers quickly create great
software prior to warp Zach was a
principal engineer at Google working on
Google Docs sheets and slides he was
also the interim CTO of time and the CTO
and co-founder of a startup called
self-made Zach welcome to software
engineering radio thank you for having
me here Gregory excited to chat today
So today we're going to be talking about
the warp command line terminal I'm
really excited about a lot of the cool
features that are in the warp terminal
and I really look forward to diving into
them
with that said I hope that you can share
a few of the key features that the warp
terminal provides and then explain why
you decided to build it sure so the
short answer is we decided to build it
because the the terminal is a I think a
very important tool to a lot of
developers most developers it's
something that they use every day but
it's also something that hasn't really
been rethought or explored from first
principles I think almost ever like the
version of the terminal developers use
today is basically identical to what
they've used for the last 40 years and
from a usability perspective we thought
that there were ways we could improve
upon it so some of the big improvements
that users will see right out of the
gate is when you use warp we actually
put structure around the output in the
terminal so we have this concept called
blocks so when you run a terminal
command we group the command and it's
output together into a block and you can
navigate your terminal on a sort of
command by command basis and you can
take easy actions on those like copy
paste you can search just within one
command's output any commands output you
can easily share so that's one big thing
that people will notice and then another
big thing is the way that input works in
warp is very different from a normal
terminal so in a normal terminal the
like the mouse doesn't work for example
and so in warp the terminal input works
a lot more like how a code editor works
like vs code or something like that so
get things like syntax highlighting you
get command completions out of the box
it's fully Mouse accessible and so those
are two of the really like key user
experience things that we launched with
and then there's also a whole bunch more
that I hope we get to talk about but
yeah those are some of the basics okay
so it sounds like warp has a lot of cool
features that standard terminal windows
don't have before we start unpacking the
many technical innovations that are in
warp I'm hoping we can and Define some
key Concepts so let's start with terms
like console terminal command line and
shell Zach can you dive in and give us a
brief definition of those types of terms
sure so they're all related so console
typically means the actual sort of
Hardware terminal I guess which is maybe
the starting spot typically when people
are using a terminal what they're
actually using is a terminal emulator
which is like a actual GUI app that you
run could be running it on your Mac your
Linux windows and what that app does is
actually emulating the behavior of the
physical piece of Hardware that people
used to regularly use and so the the
terminal has the window and it has like
it's basically like a character
rendering device and a character input
output device so it's the program that
takes input from your keyboard one
character at a time and then sends it
actually to the Shell which is another
one of the terms you mentioned the shell
is basically like the actual command
interpreter so the input to the Shell is
text it parses that text it figures out
what command that text is launching and
then the shell launches applications it
then takes the output of those
applications which again if you're in
this command line environment are
character based and sends them back to
the terminal and the terminal is
responsible for rendering the characters
on the screen so at really simple level
it's like the terminal is where the
characters are rendered and the
characters go into the shell the shell
is what understands those executes
programs and returns them back and then
the final term you mentioned is the
command line which I think is kind of
more colloquially like the whole
interface around doing these text-based
apps or at least that's how I think of
it so sometimes they'll just talk about
the command line I'm developing a
command line app and what that means is
it's an app that runs with a text-based
interface so it runs through the
terminal and shell so that makes sense
yeah that makes a lot of sense I want to
pick up on two things that you've said
so far first you mentioned that
terminals have been around for decades
and second I heard you frequently
talking about how terminals are text
based in nature can you comment quickly
why are text-based terminals so exciting
and Powerful for developers to use yeah
it's a great question because there
aren't many other 40 year old apps that
people sell regularly use what I would
say is that Terminals and text-based
apps have a bunch of inherent like
advantages compared to other types of
app so you know for one thing they're
the easiest type of app to write in a
lot of ways like most developers first
app that they write their hello world is
something that outputs text to a
terminal after that it's just very easy
to process text as an input so it's like
there's the standard format of like you
know I forget what it's like arc V and
rxc if you're writing a c app it's like
it just passes in the parameters via
text is just a much easier way to take
data input than to write something that
handles like Mouse events and renders a
rich UI so there's this advantage of
these apps being easy to write I think a
second Advantage is like they're very
fast to run and they're very lightweight
you know if you're a developer who likes
to use the keyboard a lot sort of a
lightweight execution environment for
running these apps there's even more so
from like a a UI surface standpoint I
think it's very easy to write a command
line app that is sort of infinitely
configurable just in terms of flags
whereas you start to run into the limits
of what you can do with a GUI app you
know you have to make a lot of choices
around like are you gonna have this
button or that button this form or that
form in a command line app like it's
effectively infinite you can just keep
adding Flags so there's that value
there's the value in terms of these apps
like text being a sort of universal
interface where you can take the output
of one of these command line apps and
very easily pipe it as the input it to
another one and so these apps are sort
of naturally composable and you see this
with like Unix pipelines it's really
powerful concept for how do you define
like very minimal apps that work well
together just having text as the
interface is really good for that and
then I would say one final thing is like
a lot of the way the internet works a
lot of what's like running internet
servers when you think about it are
things that are like you know Docker
containers that are essentially running
a bunch of command line apps and those
servers they don't really have like
they're not actually running guise and
so if you want to interact with them you
sort of need to be using a command line
interface I think I know that was a lot
but I do think there's a lot of these
inherent advantages to using text as the
interface that make this interface still
super relevant for developers today and
it's like it's a ubiquitous tool every
developer uses yeah I really resonated
with what you said for me the command
line terminal is also super relevant and
I use it in a wide variety of different
workflows could you share with us what
are some common workflows that you adopt
when you're using a command line
terminal it's a great question so
it's a really really flexible tool it's
almost like I sometimes use the analogy
of a spreadsheet for knowledge workers
like you can do so many different things
with it I would say just to name a few
very common ones so people will do a lot
of like source code management is very
common some developers it's still
popular as an editor so people will
still actually run like vim and emacs
and use the terminal for that attaching
to remote machines is a very popular
thing so it's like terminal like I said
if you want to access a server and
production or do some sort of debugging
on like a Raspberry Pi like typically
those machines will not have guise and
so you'll use the terminal for that
internal tooling so for developers like
I would say command line apps are still
the most popular by far way of writing
internal tools and scripts and so that
could be whatever a company wants to do
it could be like pulling information for
data analysis it could be orchestrating
you know GitHub actions and different
workflows like that always starts with
work in the terminal and so I guess one
other thing is like a lot of companies
that are Cloud providers will will build
and ship clis is one of the primary ways
for doing interactive work with whatever
their their Cloud thing is so like
gcloud or AWS a lot of the if you're
going to do interactive work as done
through the terminal so you mentioned
many of the ways that I use a terminal
on a regular basis in fact I even use a
terminal to edit all of my text because
I use a command line tool to edit text
like neovim or emacs yep exactly
so with those things in mind before we
start talking about the specifics of
warp there may be some developers who
are listening who don't normally use a
command line terminal so can you tell us
a little bit what steps would a
developer normally take if they want to
download and install and set up and
configure a command line terminal yep so
depends on what platform you're on so
typically the platforms will actually
ship with like a default terminal like
if you're on Mac there's the terminal
app if you're on I think most Linux
machines will ship with a default
console but that's like a very very Bare
Bones experience I would say so if you
want to get it to a point where you have
like a more ergonomic or efficient
experience you're typically going to
download and install a third-party
terminal there's different ones that are
popular on different platforms on Mac
there's not just warp but there's I term
there's some other terminals I think
we'll talk about later like alacrity and
Wes terms so there's a variety so the
first step is to choose what terminal
you want to use
and then depending on like the terminal
there's typically a bunch of setup that
you then go and do in your shell and
actually and maybe in the terminal too
so you might want to choose a theme
there's a lot of Open Source stuff out
there that'll make your shell experience
better this is particularly relevant if
you're not using warp like in warp one
of the things that we try to do is
actually really minimize the amount of
config that you need to make the
terminal usable but if you're using a
standard terminal you might want to like
install something that helps with auto
completions or helps with themes or you
might want to change your shell like
often the default shell might be bash
but you might want zsh or fish and so
there's a bunch of configuration to do
to figure out like how do I make this
thing usable for me you might want to
change your prompt like that's a very
common thing people do so they can see
what their current context is before
they run a command so and then there's
there's tons of resources on on the
internet and like honestly some of the
most popular open source projects on
GitHub in terms of stars or things about
making your terminal better so it's
there is a ton of information out there
if you want to like you know get get a
terminal going and then set it up I
guess one other thing I didn't mention
is like Ides will often ship with a
default terminal so that's another
option so if you're using like you know
vs code or one of the jetbrains things
there's a inbuilt terminal that comes
with it although if you want to get my
personal preference and people will vary
on this is to have a dedicated terminal
app but you can also use it within the
IDE so thanks for your responses I think
you've done an awesome job at setting
the stage let's dive into some of the
basic features that are provided by the
warp command line terminal a moment ago
you talked about something like bash
which is a shell does warp provide its
own shell or does warp integrate with
other shows like bash can you give us a
few more details
yes so as of today warp does not have
its own shell warp is compatible with
bash CSH and fish which I think are the
most
probably the three most prevalent shells
in use these days there are other shells
that are a little bit
less frequently used that we could
support but don't currently support and
the general experience with warp is that
if you download it open it up it will
use your default shell config and
hopefully like
basically just work without you having
to do any extra work to get it set up to
work with your shell so the features
that you've described in warp sound
really cool what steps would a developer
take if they want to install the warp
terminal do they go to warp.dev do they
use Homebrew do they take some other
approach can you give us some more
details Zach so those two options are
exactly right so you can go to warp.dev
and you can download the DMG and install
it like you would any other Mac app or
if you want to use Brew it's simple too
it's Brew install dash dash Cask space
warp and that will also install warp
just like any other Brew formula okay so
I know some developers may already be
using their own terminal window and they
may have even adopted the use of
something called a terminal multiplexer
like screen or tmux as we do more of a
deep dive into warp does it provide its
own terminal multiplexer or does it
integrate with existing multiplexers how
does that work Zach as a warp user you
have a couple choices and just to sort
of describe what a terminal multiplexer
is maybe for a second it's a terminal
multiplexer like tmux is it basically
lets you do things like session
management and Pain Management within a
terminal window which is useful if you
want to sort of multitask across
different terminal sessions and so for
warp the short answer is you can use
tmux or you can use screen if you use
them though you currently lose a bunch
of the stuff that makes warp like
different as a terminal so you sort of
fall back to the behavior of a of a
traditional terminal where you don't get
blocks or input editor so it's not an
awesome experience just to be honest
we're trying to figure out how to make
it better the other option if you want
that type of functionality is you don't
have to use a multiplexer like warp and
natively supports having split panes and
tabs and multiple sessions that you can
view at once within the terminal but it
doesn't yet support some of the more
advanced functionality that tmux has
around session management and it's it's
actually I think it's one of our top 10
issues on GitHub to offer better support
for that okay so that sounds really
interesting you've mentioned on more
than one occasion the idea of the
command block feature that warp provides
and I'm understanding that that feature
would be turned off if I used tmux but
let's say I wasn't using tmux can you
tell me a little bit about what the
command block feature is and how it
works
sure so the basic idea is that most not
all but most of the the way that people
use the terminal is as a sort of Rebel
so like a redevelop print Loop and what
that means is like you're either in the
state of like entering a command or
actually after you enter command it
tends to produce some output and in most
terminals the terminal just has no sense
or understanding of what the structure
of the underlying session is so the
terminal will typically have you run a
command it's just like filling up a
buffer of text and there's no uh like
demarcation between what command is
attached to what text it's just one big
buffer and so for instance if you want
to do something like copy of the output
of one of your prior commands in a
normal terminal you have to sort of you
know take your mouse and select and
scroll to just the right region and
capture just the right characters and
then you copy it and same thing if you
want to like do anything that is like
oriented around a single command output
that is very hard in a normal terminal
in warp what we do is we automatically
understand a little bit more of the
structure of what's happening and so
essentially if you were to look in the
UI we group a command with the output
that it generates and that gives you
some really nice sort of ux benefits
around things like I can very easily
navigate my command my scroll history a
command at a time for instance if I want
to scroll right to the start of a
command or right to the out end of a
command's output I can do that if I want
to search just within one command's
output I can trivially do that and
that's really useful if you like running
the same command over and over again but
just want to search for a log message in
like the last version of it if I want to
share something I did we have like a
native sharing feature that's based on
blocks so you can easily get like
essentially like a gist or a permalink
to anything you did in the terminal you
can send it to people on your team and
so the way I view this is like a new ux
primitive almost similar to like the
blocks style thing that you would get in
a Jupiter notebook or another like
structured document format that makes
you know working with terminal outputs I
think just like a lot more effective and
productive yeah I'm glad you said
Jupiter notebook because in fact that's
something that I thought of when I was
using the command block feature in warp
can you give us a concrete example how
would a command block help me if for
example I was testing or debugging my
program how would I use blocks a good
example would be like let's say you're
doing successive runs of the same
command it's producing different log
output each time and you want to just
search in the most recent invocation of
that command's output to see if a
certain debugging string is there so
what you do is you would every block we
have has like a little header and you
would just like sort of right click and
be like okay I want to search within the
contents of this block and then your
search is automatically scoped to the
last command notification and then going
further let's say okay I can't figure
out what's going on here so let me see
if someone else can look at this debug
output on who I'm working with with one
click you can grab a link to the block
send it to your teammate who can look at
the output in their browser they don't
even have to install warp and maybe they
can tell you oh I see what's going on
like the you know this is what you need
to do to debug it further and so that's
like an example of how having that extra
structure can be really helpful when
working with terminal outputs yeah I can
see that being super useful to be able
to share the output of a specific block
with a member of my team and say hey can
you figure out why this test case is
failing that would be something I would
really want to be able to do as a
developer yeah it's cool
so I know that you mentioned before the
idea of a session management and you
talked about various window management
features that warp has can we do a deep
dive into session and window management
what kinds of features does warp have in
that area and then how does it compare
to the similar terminals that might
maybe for example come on Mac OS we
offer I guess there's two big features
in warp so one is multi-tabs and so you
know if you're to look back at terminals
I don't know 10 20 years ago it was just
like you had a single terminal window
that you worked in within warp you have
the ability to have multiple sessions
and switch between them and the ways
that you can switch between or create
new sessions in warp is at the window
level so you can you can always do
command n and get a whole new terminal
window and some users like to work like
that within a window you could have tabs
and so think of like Chrome tabs
essentially where each tab is a single
terminal session or within a tab you can
have split panes and so you can actually
have side by side sessions I wouldn't
say there's anything like particularly
groundbreaking about warp at least right
now in this respect it's like sort of On
a par with some of the other terminals
on Mac that ship with this type of
session management it is all keyboard
accessible so it's like if you want to
quickly navigate between ones or others
you can do that we have another feature
that's actually pretty cool and popular
which is something that we call the
official name is like a hotkey window
but the colloquial name is a quake quake
mode window and what that does is it
lets you assign a sort of global
keyboard shortcut which no matter what
application you're using you have the
ability to get like a warp terminal to
sort of modally pop up in front of you
and you know it's called this because I
think in the video game Quake there was
a this sort of same terminal that you
could pull up anywhere and so we have
that too so yeah those are some of the
cool like window and tab management
functions that we have in warp right now
yeah I'm familiar with the feature that
you talked about and I have to say it is
cool to be able to have a warp terminal
zoom in regardless of the program that
I'm currently using
so in summary we said that like for
example you could have maybe one pain in
warp that is related to testing and I
could have another pain that's related
to running a compiler and I could have
another one of the pains that was
related to like for example running a
server or something of that nature are
there any limits in terms of the way
that I lay out my pains or lay out my
tabs or is is warp configurable in that
fashion it's totally configurable and
then we have actually one other thing
which I should have mentioned which is
this concept of a launch configuration
and so you can actually create a like a
yaml file which says I think your
example is a good one it's like hey I
know that when I'm working on this
project I always want one window for the
client I want one window for the server
I want one window for connecting to
production so you can Define that in a
file and then you can launch that
configuration as sort of like one Atomic
thing so that you can quickly get the
setup that you want okay so is there
away for example that I can have one set
up when I'm building one program and
another setup when I'm building another
program 100 yeah you can define those as
like two separate uh launch
configuration files and then you know in
work we have this feature called the
command palette which you can push
command P wherever you are and one of
the options from there is launching one
of these launch configurations and it
will just bring up a window that has the
exact pane sizes programs running that
you want so that you you can waste less
time getting set up and you can context
switch much more easily that sounds
really cool so we've talked about a
number of the key features that warp
provides I remember a while ago you
talked about the idea of warp offering a
completion menu what is a completion
menu and how does a developer use it
yeah so I'd say the command line has a
bunch of awesome attributes around its
ux being very fast and extensible but
one of the challenges around the command
line UI X is like you have to remember
how these infinitely flexible commands
are actually used and so documentation
and discoverability around how to use
commands is is a challenge for this kind
of interface so one of the things that
we offer is we help you complete
commands and command completion is a
standard shell feature that you will see
in all sorts of shells but in warp it's
actually quite different because we've
implemented it at the level of the
terminal and what that means is like you
get essentially a visual completion menu
which you know if you're an IDE user if
you use vs code or jetbrains will be
familiar with you and so we're able to
as you like start typing a command if
you push tab and you can configure this
but as you push tab we bring up these
visual completion menus which give you
an ordered set of our best guests at
what the next thing that you might want
to enter is so if you do like git space
and then hit tab you get options of like
all the git commands if you start typing
CH then it filters down to like get
checkout so it you know it filters as
you type to the most likely suggestion
and then another sort of unique thing
about warp that we offer that other
terminals don't offer is we give you
actual documentation as you type around
what these commands mean and so if you
have something with like obscure flags
and you're like remind me what dash dash
force does or something like that then
we can actually in line show you okay
this is what this flag means and you can
bring that documentation back up
whenever you want it to so if you can
position the cursor and hit command I
and you'll get the documentation you can
hover and get that same documentation so
I mean that's a it's my knowledge a
totally unique feature at the terminal
level in warp and so that's a I think a
real user advantage and then you don't
have to configure this in warp either so
you know typically if you want
completions and it gets a good example
you have to put something in your RC
file in like one of your startup files
that will Source those completions and
make the shell aware of them so they're
available and warp all this stuff just
ships out of the box which is very nice
so the features you're describing sound
really useful if I am already using for
example fish and fish provides
completion does that completion work
alongside of the completion that we're
provides how does that work
so Wars is typically takes it over and
this is a I would say it's a trade-off
so we try to do the best that we can
shipping out of the box with completion
and we ship with like
400 or 500 tools I forget the exact
number but if you've configured things
at the Shell level because in warp we
sort of take over the entire shell input
editor we aren't able to use those
completions it's a thing that we're
we've like considered like and it's
maybe getting technically in the weeds
of like is there a way to use the
Shell's completions with acceptable sort
of performance characteristics and mix
them in with our own the war points tend
to be super super low latency because
it's all like natively bundled into our
app whereas when you've kind of like go
out to the Shell for questions it
becomes a little bit slower and then the
shell ones don't have the same spec
format as ours like they don't give you
documentation and so you know as of
right now this is a real trade-off it's
definitely something that users of warp
give us feedback on and we're you know
we're trying to figure out what is the
best possible solution but it's a great
question okay so right now it seems like
War basically takes over your command
line completion if I start running a
text editor inside of my warp terminal
window does it also take over the
completion of neovim or emacs what
happens in that case
in that case everything works just as it
normally would so in general again this
will be a little bit technical but I
think that's okay like there's a couple
modes of running the terminal there's
the the like the rebel mode where you
know warp is providing the command line
editor and doing things like completions
and then there's the mode that you go
into when you run an app like Vim or
emacs which is actually using a
different character buffer which we call
it the alt Grid or the alt screen and in
those types of apps good examples like
Vim emacs top those fully interactive
like Tui like text user interface based
apps warps behavior is exactly the same
as a normal terminal and so you know a
lot of people use Vim plus warp emacs
plus warp and that all just works
exactly as you would expect it to okay
that makes a lot of sense I often do
development of my own command line
applications so if I'm using the go
programming language or Python and I'm
building my own command line interface
does warp integrate with it in terms of
providing completion of its command line
arguments
so sort of the way that that works is
there's an open source repo that we use
that has the specs for all of these
different completions it's actually run
by another startup which is called fig
where they've defined a spec that's in
it's in Json and it gives you like the
ability to say like okay here's here's
what this command looks like here are
all the flags here's what they mean we
then take that repo and translate into
something that we can use which is in
Rust if you want to support new tools at
least for now until we have a sort of
more fleshed out Solution on the warp
side what you would do is you would make
a submission to that repo and it would
eventually make it into Warp the longer
term solution for us is to actually
create a sort of spec where you don't
have to publicly publish your command
line like a lot of use cases for this
type of thing or people's internal tools
or private tools and I think the right
solution is something like there is a
spec that you can publish and just limit
the scope of without putting it out
fully open source into the world and
maybe just use it yourself even if you
want and that's something that's on our
roadmap it's actually this coming
quarter we're going to be working on the
start of this yeah what you're
describing would be really helpful to me
as a terminal window because I've
implemented a bunch of my own programs
and they're not in that repo and I may
not even want to publish the details
about my own programs so if there was a
way that I could make warp aware of my
own command line applications that would
really be awesome that's 100 how it
should work and that's on our on our
roadmap we're just not quite there yet
okay so we've talked about a lot of the
features that warp provides and I want
to dive into some of the more advanced
features of the warp command line
terminal so there's a whole bunch that
I'd like to talk about but let's start
with the ways in which warp uses the GPU
or the graphics Processing Unit can you
talk a little bit about why your
terminal uses the GPU and what are the
benefits associated with using a GPU the
primary reason that that we use the GPU
is performance you know when you're a
developer using the terminal there's a
lot of reasons why you might want to use
the terminal but one of the things I
think that's absolutely essential is
that the terminal performs really really
well and you can think of different
dimensions of performance like there's a
dimension of just like pure input output
operations so that's like how quickly do
characters go
from the terminal into the shell and
then more importantly typically from a
shell program back into the terminal but
there's also a big performance that I
would think of more in terms of graphics
performance almost things that like if
you're a video game developer you might
care about so it's like what's the frame
rate in which we can render terminal
changes and like how fast can you scroll
around your terminal and these are you
know operations that become really
important if you're if you're doing
things that work with a lot of text
you know the sort of non-gpu way of
doing it is using a more like CPU or
software-based rendering framework the
performance of the gpu-based way of
doing it is is certainly better what it
means for you know a terminal like warp
is that we are interfacing directly with
the graphics apis on Mac and what that
looks like is that you're actually you
know you're writing code in a Shader
language on Mac it's uh the Shader
language is is metal which is somewhat
similar to like opengl and it's a you
know it's a very different style of
programming you're basically writing
Graphics operations that have to be able
to run you know in parallel and you're
running Shader code that gets shipped to
a GPU but yeah the basic sorry
long-winded answer here is like it's
faster okay so it's faster and I'm
assuming it's faster from the
perspective of user perceived latency
when you use the when you use the GPU
for doing the rendering of text in the
warp terminal does it also reduce things
like the system load how does it work in
terms of things Beyond user perceived
latency
so I think user perceived latency is is
the biggest one you know I haven't
written a text rendering thing that uses
the CPU so it's a little bit hard for me
to sort of compare what it what it would
be like but in general I think we're
doing it in in the most efficient in the
most efficient way because it is not
like pegging the CPU in packing system
load as you do this it's doing it on a
totally different piece of hardware and
yeah I mean these are like generally I
think this is the most efficient way
that you can do the graphic stuff is by
going directly to the GPU and not
forcing your CPU to do a bunch of math
to figure out how to like draw paths and
render glyphs
so you mentioned metal and we're going
to talk about Metal later in the show
because I think it's important to dive
into how you implemented warp in Rust
and how you use metal on Mac OS before
we do that can you give an example of
what a terminal would be like if it
didn't use the GPU what would we forego
if warp didn't use the GPU so I'm
winging it here slightly because I
haven't built a non-gpu based terminal
but what I think you would do instead is
you would use a set of higher level UI
libraries where you would do things like
it could be like a like a vector style
API like you could be drawing lines and
curves you could be telling it to print
out text directly But ultimately like
the there wouldn't be such a clean set
of Graphics programs that are that there
would be a lot of processing on the
actual CPU to figure out where the pixel
should be painted on the screen you know
I'm trying to think of a good example
here like if you were to do this using
like just the straight up Apple apis I
don't think that everything would be
Graphics except like GPU accelerated
meaning like if you were to use like an
NS View and an NS label and like those
sort of higher level UI components I
don't think you end up with a GPU
accelerated thing all of the time
because there's a lot of intermediate
processing on the CPU in a to figure out
how to render everything okay so that
makes a lot of sense it sounds like
overall when warp uses the GPU I'm going
to see that my terminal window has like
a better frames per second yep okay it's
going to reduce the load on my CPU which
can be used for other things so overall
it sounds like using the GPU gives me a
better experience as a user of the warp
terminal window
for sure okay those are the exact two
benefits that you mentioned yeah so what
I'd like to do now is to turn our
attention to some of the innovative ways
in which warp uses artificial
intelligence I learned that warp
integrates AI directly into the terminal
my big question is what in the world
does it mean to integrate AI into a
terminal window
it's a great question and it's I think
it's an important question because of
the amount of hype there is around AI
right now but in the terminal it's
actually super super useful so for us
with AI there's sort of two main ways of
interacting with it the first way is
like it allows you to go from natural
language to a command and so this is
super useful so it's like say I want to
write a command that allows me to find
all rust files greater than 100 lines
long and then extract a certain term
from them or something like that I don't
know how to write that command I could
Google I could leave the context of the
terminal I could ask a friend maybe who
like knows the way it works better but
the easiest thing by far is to just ask
the terminal hat this is what I want to
do can you help write the command for me
and like more often than not with these
large language models the um the command
that comes back Works which is
incredible so you go from a very
obscure-like way of like expressing your
intent which is these you know the
commands instead of having to actually
write them out like that you can simply
just say a natural language
so that's one entry point one I think
very cool way of using it the second one
is like a more conversational mode and
so this is more similar to you know how
you might use chat GPT Bard or another
one of these like llm chat Bots the
thing that makes it super useful in the
terminal is the integration with command
input inputs and outputs so for instance
if you
you run some gcloud command and it
produces some permissions there and
you're like oh no what do I do to fix
that like it's very it's trivial and
warped to be like okay let me ask warp
AI how do I fix this thing that went
wrong so you can go right from an error
to a conversation about how to fix it
and that conversation will often produce
new commands and those new commands you
can directly run and so you have a very
tight feedback loop when you're trying
to figure out how to solve problems in
the command line and so it's kind of an
awesome use case for it and like it's
made even better by the fact that these
llms are all they speak text and the
terminal speaks text so it's very simple
to go right from terminal input output
into the llm and back and then these
llms they're often trained on a lot of
sort of command line data like if you
look at stack Overflow and look at the
internet there's a ton of training data
around API documentation on how to
actually use these tools better so it's
it's a really like really good apple
education and technology for making the
command line better so what you're
saying sounds really compelling and I
see what you're getting at because of
the fact the terminal window is text
centered and these AI large language
models are also text centered it's
really cool to pull those two things
together inside of the word command line
terminal
absolutely it works really really well
like we
you know we survey users about it
they're like this is you know pretty
game changing and it's like it just
saves a whole context switch and lets
you get to
it just lets you get to the answer that
you want faster and with like less of a
headache and the the conversational
stuff is extra cool because it you know
it remembers the context as you build up
a conversation so if you could be like
it knows that I'm trying to to achieve
some tasks and gcloud it can use prior
questions to inform the next answer that
it gives it's very powerful can you tell
us a little bit about how you actually
implemented warp AI what are you using
to create this powerful feature
yeah so right now warp AI is built on
top of open AI their chat GPT model and
so the main like
you know the main like challenges on our
side were like how do you engineer The
Prompt correctly so that you get back
meaningful results for the command line
how do you find the right integration
points into the UI for the for the AI
and so you know you want to balance
making it discoverable and making it
useful with like you don't want to annoy
people like you don't want like the
Microsoft clippy thing I don't think at
least like maybe that was before it's
time and the right way to do it but it's
like I don't think you want like AI
things popping up everywhere in the
terminal especially since like it's a
tool people like do a lot of focus work
in and so you have to balance those
things and then a third thing for us is
like you really have to balance privacy
and security so it's like Rai at the
moment you have to opt in to use it
every time you want to use it just
because a lot of private information
flows through the terminal and currently
the model is not a local model which it
would be interesting to see if we could
get to a local model but the model is a
cloud-based model and so we want to be
very careful people being clear if like
hey this information is being sent off
the terminal people should know that and
choose to be doing it so you mentioned
that right now you're using a
cloud-based model can you give us a
concrete example if I have a compiler
error or if my program crashes or if it
produces uses output that I think would
be wrong how can warp AI help me in
those types of circumstances yeah so
compiler error is easy this is a great
example of how some of our features tie
together so say you try to compile and
you get a compiler error and so let's
say that error then would be contained
in one block and so we know that the
block has an error code in it and so
that you can go right from the Block to
something called ask warp Ai and so you
just with a keyboard shortcut or a click
you're like hey explain this error to me
and then warp AI comes back with like a
this is what the error means and here's
a suggested fix so that's one concrete
use case another concrete use case is
less around writing code and more like
doing something in production and so
like a real thing that I tried to do was
I wanted to figure out how to access
logs and tail logs in the terminal from
one of our production servers that's
running on gcloud that's not a one
command thing that's like a you know
first I need to list all the instances
then I need to find like the name of
them and then I need to make sure I'm
like like correctly set up to access
things through the firewall and so it
will do a like a guided sequence of
commands with you to get you to the
right Point including answering like if
you run a command and it's like that
instance doesn't exist it will try and
give you ideas on how to debug getting
to the right thing so super powerful for
those types of production use cases yeah
I can imagine that that would be
incredibly helpful for me as a developer
can you comment quickly if my program
crashes and there's a stack Trace in the
terminal window can warp AI help me to
understand that stack Trace
100 yeah so you just go ask warp Ai and
if you want to ask a particular you
could either just be like tell me what's
going on or you can ask a particular
question like you know why is this
having a null pointer exception why did
this seg fault or you know and like
it will do its best now I will say these
the the AI models have limits like and
they are prone to hallucination
sometimes so it's like use it with care
like they'll I've had situations where
it will refer me to documentation
websites that don't exist or like
confidently tell me to do something that
isn't quite right so I would certainly
like use your judgment but as a an aide
to solving things quickly there it's
it's a phenomenal technology
so a moment ago you mentioned the idea
of using a local first model before we
talk about the local first approach I
wanted to clarify one quick issue is
warp AI actually sending to the cloud
the source code of my application or is
it exclusively using the text that it
sees in the terminal window it's
exclusively using what you directly give
it on a per invocation basis so there is
absolutely no like background sending of
someone's context or data in our current
implementation now that said I actually
think
the AI would be significantly more
powerful if we were able to provide more
context but we've taken a very
conservative approach again because of
like privacy and security concerns so
right now to answer your question it's
like you basically you can see in our
sort of input area exactly what's being
sent and there's no more than that being
said okay thanks for clarifying that
let's dive into the idea of a local
first model what is a local first model
and what are the trade-offs associated
with using it either as a substitute for
a cloud-based model or perhaps in
conjunction with a cloud-based model
yeah so local first just means like we
wouldn't be using the network at all to
sort of generate suggestions or AI
responses
there's different ways that you can you
can do this the the sort of trade-offs I
think are in terms of like model size
sophistication disk space like resources
to run the sort of inference step and so
then there's also like on the plus side
there's increased privacy security like
you have confidence stuff's not leaving
your computer it works even if you don't
happen to be connected to the internet
which is you know like something that
warp we generally strive for is warp
should always work like you shouldn't
have to have an internet connection to
use your terminal like we want graceful
fallback with that but today it's like
you you need an internet connection to
use warp Ai and so you know I think
there could be benefits around latency
as well like right now we have you know
Network latency although I would say
most of the actual latency is in the
inference like the mod like the actual
like performance of the prediction on
the model side not the network but
having a uh something that's local could
be really really good especially for
super highly latency sensitive
operations so like for instance we
wanted to do something like predict your
next command as you're typing that's a
very latency sensitive thing where you
don't want three seconds to pass as
you're typing to get the prediction you
want you know sub 100 milliseconds worth
of latency so that it seems like it's
just happening in real time those are
some of the trade-offs yeah what you're
saying makes a lot of sense ultimately
are you considering some type of hybrid
approach where sometimes you use a
cloud-based model other times you use a
local model what's on your roadmap Zach
yeah so I mean we want to work backwards
from like what's going to be best for
users yeah it could be some sort of
hybrid it could be that
you know even there's a third option
which is like a self-hosted model for
organizations that's cloud-based but not
on uh you know using open AIS public
apis and so there's a lot of different
ways that we could do this and we're
still
I'd say we're still very early on we
launched our first iteration of this
about two months ago and it's it's
something new is happening in AI every
single day we are actively trying to
figure out what's going to be the best
user experience that's ultimately what's
going to drive it yeah it could be some
hybrid thanks for the insights that
you've shared about how you use AI in
warp I think you mentioned a really good
point which is you want a terminal
window that's best for developers and
obviously you made a decision to
implement the war terminal window in
Rust because it was going to be best for
developers can you share a little bit
about the key features of the rust
programming language and why you decided
to use rust for your implementation sure
so Russ is a great language it's I think
you typically call it like a systems
language it compiles down to uh to
Binary it is
I don't know I'm probably gonna not
describe this in a way that rust
enthusiasts like but it's almost like a
the Next Generation safer more ergonomic
version of C plus in a lot of ways it's
not really object oriented in the way
that c plus is some of the benefits are
produces very fast code so that was
again like we're hyper performance
focused but it's very fast code it has a
it does this by sort of like a unique
memory management model where
in rusts there is like a concept of like
ownership of references and sort of
moving references that is very different
than in most languages and you know Russ
consequently is is not a garbage
collected language so there's no
overhead of a garbage collector
it's also not a sort of manual memory
allocation and freeing language so you
don't have a lot of the issues that can
cause you know sort of memory safety
errors or seg faults or that type of
stuff that you get in C plus plus it has
its own very unique model of like who
owns what value and as a programmer it
actually I would say it takes like a
fair amount of getting used to like like
something that you know you expect to be
like an assignment operation is often
more of a move operation in Rust where
you're moving ownership and so you do
spend more time I'd say fighting the
compiler than you do in most languages
but once you learn it I think it's
actually a very ergonomic language to
work in it has great community support
and it has great cross-platform support
which is another really really key thing
for us so you know you can compile warp
apps for for most platforms including
the web platform which is I think maybe
we'll talk about this in a bit but it's
a platform that we really care about
supporting at warp and so I would say of
all of the the languages maybe besides
typescript but maybe even better than
typescript warp has a compilation to
webassembly which is a path that we want
to use to bring warp to the web and so
we've had an awesome experience using
it's a great great programming language
so we'll talk about using warp in the
web browser in a moment it sounds like
one of the things that you're saying is
that there's a learning curve associated
with rust but if you want to make a high
performance terminal window rust is a
really good language to pick I think
it's the best I would say for a
combination of high performance
multi-platform it's the best option you
know the other big multi-platform option
is the common option is to build it in
web technology we prototyped warp as an
electron app using like typescript and
the performance was far far worse like
you just start at a sort of like
performance debt is almost how I would
say like you pay for a lot of the
overhead of what browsers are built to
do which is not like high performance
viewported like terminal rendering and I
know this also from my time building
Google Docs like which has a lot of the
same sort of Performance challenges I
wish that we would use something like
rust and wasm to do it because it's just
very very hard to get Optimal
Performance out of JavaScript plus the
Dom and so that those are the reasons
why we went with rust yeah what you're
saying makes a lot of sense I remember
earlier you mentioned that you use metal
which is the Mac OS GPU new API can you
talk a little bit about how rust and
metal work together in the warp command
line terminal yeah so
the way that we use metal so metal is a
set of Graphics apis that let you access
the GPU on Macs and the sort of language
that metal works with is is this Shader
language for metal so like if you're
writing you know metal shaders it kind
of looks like you're writing shaders in
opengl or webgl you're writing fragment
shaders and you're writing pixel shaders
and you're writing things that go into
like the graphics Pipeline and so that's
not written in Rust that's written in
actual metal Shader language what we do
with rust is we have a sort of platform
abstraction where we've actually built
our own sort of you know lightweight UI
framework where if you want to be able
to say like okay give me a give me a
rectangle that has text inside of it
with rounded Corners you don't have to
like go all the way down to the Shader
code to do that like that would be
insane to write you write it and what we
do is we construct a scene and this all
happens in Rust The Scene goes down onto
a set of Primitives that map one to one
into the Shader language and it's
actually very few Primitives super cool
so all you really need to render a
terminal is the ability to render like a
rectangle and that rectangle can have
borders backgrounds round corners that
type of stuff you need to be able to
render glyphs and so like the text
rendering is one of the more complex
parts of our rendering Pipeline and you
need to be able to render like images
and icons
and that almost honestly gets you
everything like those are The Primitives
and so what our rust-based UI framework
does is essentially translate higher
level things into those what ends up
being a sequence of Graphics calls to
draw Rex glyphs and images and so you
know you go from rusts into those
Graphics calls the graphics calls have
to actually happen
uh like Objective C because like so we
there's Russ allows you to sort of do
something like I think it's the foreign
function interface it lets you bind into
native platform code selectively if you
need to and so you know 95 of our app is
rust but the pieces that are like hey we
need to call them uh you know metal we
need to actually do that from Objective
C and so you bind in the native code to
do that
so thanks a lot for giving us the
overview of how warp was implemented
using rust and using metal one of the
things that I can tell really clearly is
that performance is Central to your work
so my question is how do you make sure
that when you ship a new version of warp
that you've maintained your performance
goals it's a great question and it's
really hard I'd say there's like a few
General approaches so one one approach
is benchmarking and so you know we have
a sort of Suite of benchmarks that we
can run against warp and make sure that
we are you know performing well at least
against other terminals we are we're in
terms of like where we're at that it's
like we're not necessarily the fastest
terminal on the market for every single
operation but we are a very fast
terminal like for most operations and so
that's the way we compare the
competition the other thing is harder is
like regression like preventing
regressions and performance and so you
know there's different approaches I've
used in my career for this what we use
at Warp right now like we don't have an
environment in which we can consistently
like get like sandbox performance data
so we tend to use more like looking at
actual stats of work performance in the
wild which is which is gives you okay
view in the aggregate but it has several
problems it doesn't give you like a way
of preventing a progression until it's
live
the ideal thing that I've actually did
at Google which is not a thing that's
easy to do or at least I haven't found a
great solution was having a suite of
performance tests that could that could
run and you could run them as part of
your continuous integration to make sure
that you're not addressing things very
very hard because there's a lot of
um a lot of noise and you need like a
very controlled environment to get like
sort of accurate regression tests but
yeah those those are the different ways
that I can think of thanks for sharing
all of the ways in which you're using
rust to implement the warp terminal
window I know that ultimately your goal
is to ensure that warp can run on Mac OS
Windows Linux and ultimately the web can
you tell us a little bit about the steps
you're going to take to make warp work
in all of those locations yeah we're
working on this right now actually so
Linux is our number one requested user
feature you know we're fortunate in
using rust that all of the
non-platform specific parts of our code
will basically just compile for for like
Linux and windows for the web it's
trickier because there's some sort of
like threading and async Primitives that
we use in Rust that don't like translate
that cleanly to the web execution model
model so it's taking a little bit more
work to sort of do a platform
compilation for web but for the most
part the rust code will compile the
pieces that are platform specific tend
to be harder and so that is like text
rendering like getting like the actual
like glyphs is a platform specific thing
and getting the like the text shaping
and all the like text metrics that you
need to actually lay out text because we
we depend on the OS to tell us how to do
that windowing like different platforms
have different sort of windowing
Primitives that we need to hook into
um the event Loop so different like os's
will emit different types of events and
so we have a platform abstraction or a
code that lets us like you know
basically like know when we're leaving
like the shared code into the non-shared
code into the platform specific code but
that's basically the work of it is like
first you got to get the rust to compile
and then you have to fill in all of the
platform specific pieces and then I
guess the the final thing is like these
different platforms have different
distribution mechanisms and packaging
mechanisms so like you know for Mac it's
DMG and Homebrew for Linux it's building
for a bunch of different like Linux
distributions for Windows I don't really
even I don't know we haven't looked
closely and then obviously for the web
it's like surveying warp as a big you
know wasm slash JavaScript bundle that
gets downloaded so we have to to figure
all that out so it sounds like you have
a lot of work ahead of you can you give
us one concrete example of how someone
would use warp on the web and how would
it be similar to or different from the
way they use warp on their Mac OS
desktop the big sort of product
innovations that we're trying to bring
to the terminal is to make it work not
just for individuals but for teams and
so one of the features I talked about
earlier like the ability to like take a
block get a get a link to it and share
it to people on your team is the start
of that but there's more to it like we
would like to be able to actually not
just share a block but share an entire
session and you can do that you know we
could build that within the native app
so that if both people have
uh the Mac app installed they can you
know share the session in the Mac App
but I think it's actually a more
powerful primitive to be able to let
people to open up a terminal session in
their browser especially if that
terminal session is fast and has all of
the warp features which is what we're
building towards and so terminal session
sharing is one example there's other
examples around knowledge sharing where
it's like you want to be able to link to
terminal documentation and have other
people on your team use it we are I
think by the you know the time this
podcast comes out we'll have launched an
actual feature in warp that is a sort of
multiplayer feature where people can
store and share terminal commands and
soon notebooks and so all that stuff all
these sharing features I think are much
more powerful in the web the second
thing is like I do feel like the world
of development will eventually move from
being just like development on your
local machine to you know primarily
development on remote machines I think
it's gonna take a long time to get there
be because people's setups are so
complicated and there's actual
advantages to being local but in a world
where you're not developing on your
local machine it's actually you know
there's a lot of advantages to having a
web-based rendering it's like you can
look at the thing from your phone or
from your laptop or like so you know the
web does give you a lot of benefits and
we're trying to position ourselves to
take advantage of those yeah I can
imagine it being really compelling to be
able to use warp locally and then when I
want to Loop in some of my colleagues on
my team I can have them work with me on
warp running in my web browser exactly
like we feel like that's a potentially
such a cool killer use case whether it's
for teams or for classes or you know for
people doing firefighting to just have a
one common view like you have in
something like Google Docs I think it
could be transformative and so the web
it's not strictly necessary for that but
it makes it so much easier and better so
at this point we've covered many of the
basic and advanced features of warp and
I think you've done a really great job
of sharing those exciting ways in which
we as listeners of software engineering
radio can dive in and use warp are there
any features of warp that we didn't talk
about that you would like to highlight I
mean the one that I was going to call
out was this thing called warp drive
which is which will be launched by the
time this is out you know I'd love for
anyone who is using warp in a team
setting to try it out and like give us
feedback it's a totally novel thing
where it's like hey I have you know
these five commands that I use to talk
to gcloud which could then be shared
with your team and you could all use
them so I'm super interested in in any
feedback on that other stuff I don't
know we have we have some really cool
stuff around theming that's always a lot
of fun like people can go in and play
with our themes and like we have a
community oriented way of people
submitting themes so if you want to you
know make a theme for us and share it
that's always cool but no I think we
covered most of the most of the cool
stuff so that's awesome as we're drawing
our episode of software engineering
radio to a conclusion I want to turn to
you as an expert both in using a
terminal and also in developing and
shipping a terminal can you give a call
to action for our listeners when it
comes to terminals or developer tools or
the warp command line terminal in
specific so I'd love for folks to try
warp and give us feedback obviously I
would say if you're a developer who's
not much of a terminal user or who has
been intimidated or turned off or just
like not wanted to bother with the setup
and headache of getting a good terminal
environment I would you know hey I would
give terminals a try because I do think
there's huge productivity gains for
people who really know how to use them
well I would say like warp is probably
the easiest way to get in or at least
like that's our our goal is to make it
the easiest and most powerful experience
but I don't know I'm a really big fan of
a command line as a way of increasing
your productivity and increasing your
skill as an engineer you know most of
the really the best Engineers I know
they do stuff in the command line that
feels like magic to me and it saves them
a bunch of time so my pitch would be
like you know give it a shot and spend
some time you know learning the
communities I think could really up your
your game as a developer in general
all right thanks for that call to action
is there anything that we didn't talk
about in this episode that you'd like to
share before we draw things to a
conclusion I don't think so I you know I
would just say there's I know there's
probably a lot of great Engineers
listening to the show we work in Rust if
you're interested in how do you help
developers ship better software more
quickly if you're interested in
terminals we'd love to hear from you and
all that information is on our website
which is warp.dev which is also where
you can download and try out work all
right so this has been an awesome
conversation I've really been Keen to
learn more about warp I hope that people
will try warp out and get in contact
with you if anyone wants to learn more
about warp or the way in which warp was
implemented they're welcome to check the
show notes for this episode to catch
many of the details that Zach and I will
pass along to you Zach thanks for being
here on software engineering radio
Gregory thank you so much for having me
this was fantastic all right thanks for
being here back this is Gregory
kaphammer signing off for software
engineering radio
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se.radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack Channel at SC radio dot
slack.com you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening